<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<refentry id="ctrlproxyrc.5">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>ctrlproxyrc</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
	<refname>ctrlproxyrc</refname>
	<refpurpose>Configuration file for ctrlproxy</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsect1>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>
Ctrlproxy uses an XML file for configuration. Check the 
ctrlproxyrc.example file for a good example. There are a few 
so-called 'sections' in the file that are discussed below.
</para>

<refsect2>
	<title>plugins</title>

<para>
	This section contains a list of all the plugins that are to be loaded. A &lt;plugin&gt;
tag specifies a plugin. The 'file' attribute specifies the location the 
plugin can be found. Additional attributes or child elements can be specified, 
depending on the plugin.
</para>
</refsect2>

<refsect2>
	<title>networks</title>

<para>
This section contains a list of all the servers to join. The &lt;network&gt; element
supports the attributes: nick, username, fullname, type, pass. 
</para>

<para>
pass contains the password to join the server. client_pass contains 
the password any client that connects to the proxy should send.
</para>

<para>
The &lt;network&gt; element supports the child element &lt;channel&gt;. Attributes 
of this element are name (indicating the name of the channel) and 
autojoin (whether or not to join the channel on start).
</para>

<para>
Each &lt;network&gt; element contains a &lt;servers&gt; element which contains 
several transport-specific elements. The standard 'socket' module provides 
the transports 'ipv4', 'ipv6' and 'pipe'.
</para>

</refsect2>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>SEE ALSO</title>

<para>ctrlproxy (1), ctrlproxyrc.example, http://jelmer.vernstok.nl/oss/ctrlproxy, http://xmlsoft.org/</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>LICENSE</title>

<para>
This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
(at your option) any later version.
</para>

<para>
This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
\fBWITHOUT ANY WARRANTY\fR; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU 
General Public License for more details.
</para>

<para>
You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License 
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple PLace, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

<para>
<ulink url="mailto:jelmer@nl.linux.org">Jelmer Vernooij</ulink>
</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
